{
  "subject": "General Mathematics",
  "examQuestions": [
    {
        "question": "A group of students were asked to name their favourite colour. The results are displayed in the percentage segmented bar chart below. The percentage of students who named blue as their favourite colour is closest to A. 14% В. 18% C. 26% D. 74%",
        "answer": "B",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Freddie organised a function at work. He surveyed the staff about their preferences. He asked them about their payment preference (cash or electronic payment) and their budget preference (less than $50 or more than $50). The variables in this survey, payment preference and budget preference, are A. both categorical variables. B. both numerical variables. C. categorical and numerical variables, respectively. D. numerical and categorical variables, respectively.",
        "answer": "A",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "The histogram below displays the population density, in people per km², of the 27 countries in the European Union in 2021. The histogram has a logarithmic (base 10) scale. Question 3: The median value occurs in a column with a frequency of A. 2 B. 3 C. 6 D. 9",
        "answer": "D",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "The histogram below displays the population density, in people per km², of the 27 countries in the European Union in 2021. The histogram has a logarithmic (base 10) scale. There is one outlier at the upper end of the histogram. This value could be A. 330 B. 1330 C. 2030 D. 2730",
        "answer": "C",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "The number of siblings of each member of a class of 24 students was recorded. The results are displayed in the table below. 2 1 3 2 1 1 1 1 4 1 1 1 1 1 2 1 2 2 1 3 4 2 2 3 1. A boxplot was constructed to display the spread of the data. Which one of the following statements about this boxplot is correct? A. There are no outliers. B. The value of the interquartile range (IQR) is 1.5 C. The value of the median is 1.5 D. All of the five-number summary values are whole numbers.",
        "answer": "C",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "More than 11,000 athletes from more than 200 countries competed in the Tokyo Summer Olympic Games. An analysis of the number of athletes per country produced the following five-number summary. Minimum 2, First quartile 5, Median 11, Third quartile 48, Maximum 613. The smallest number of athletes per country that would display as an outlier on a boxplot of this data is A. 49 B. 112 C. 113 D. 613",
        "answer": "C",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Fiona plays nine holes of golf each week, and records her score. Her mean score for all rounds in 2024 is 55.7. In one round, when she recorded a score of 48, her standardised score was z = -1.75. The standard deviation for score in 2024 is A. 1.1 B. 2.3 C. 4.4 D. 6.95",
        "answer": "C",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "The scatterplot below displays the average number of female athletes per competing nation, females, against the number of the Summer Olympic Games, number, from the first Olympic Games, in 1896, to the 29th Olympic Games, held in 2021. A least squares line has been fitted to the scatterplot. The equation of the least squares line is closest to A. females = -4.87 + 1.02 × number B. females = -3.39 + 0.91 × number C. number = -3.39 + 0.91 × females D. number = -0.91 + 3.39 × females",
        "answer": "B",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "The least squares equation for the relationship between the average number of male athletes per competing nation, males, and the number of the Summer Olympic Games, number, is males = 67.5 – 1.27 × number. The summary statistics for the variables number and males are shown in the table below. Mean: number 15.0, males 48.4. Standard deviation: number 8.51, males 19.0. The value of Pearson’s correlation coefficient, r, rounded to three decimal places, is closest to A. -0.569 B. -0.394 C. 0.394 D. 0.569.",
        "answer": "A",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "The least squares equation for the relationship between the average number of male athletes per competing nation, males, and the number of the Summer Olympic Games, number, is males = 67.5 – 1.27 × number. At which Summer Olympic Games will the predicted average number of males be closest to 25.6? A. 31st B. 32nd C. 33rd D. 34th.",
        "answer": "C",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "The number of breeding pairs of a small parrot species has been declining over recent years. The table below shows the number of breeding pairs counted, pairs, and the year number, year, for the last 12 years. The association between pairs and year is non-linear. Table: year: 1, pairs: 320; year: 2, pairs: 250; year: 3, pairs: 225; year: 4, pairs: 208; year: 5, pairs: 190; year: 6, pairs: 180; year: 7, pairs: 170; year: 8, pairs: 165; year: 9, pairs: 160; year: 10, pairs: 158; year: 11, pairs: 155; year: 12, pairs: 150. The scatterplot shows a decreasing, non-linear trend of pairs versus year, starting at (1, 320) and ending at (12, 150). Question 11: The scatterplot can be linearised using a logarithmic (base 10) transformation applied to the explanatory variable. The least squares equation calculated from the transformed data is closest to A. log₁₀(pairs) = 2.44 – 0.0257 × year B. log₁₀(pairs) = 151 – 303 × year C. pairs = 274 – 12.3 × log₁₀(year) D. pairs = 303 – 151 × log₁₀(year).",
        "answer": "D",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "The number of breeding pairs of a small parrot species has been declining over recent years. The table below shows the number of breeding pairs counted, pairs, and the year number, year, for the last 12 years. The association between pairs and year is non-linear. Table: year: 1, pairs: 320; year: 2, pairs: 250; year: 3, pairs: 225; year: 4, pairs: 208; year: 5, pairs: 190; year: 6, pairs: 180; year: 7, pairs: 170; year: 8, pairs: 165; year: 9, pairs: 160; year: 10, pairs: 158; year: 11, pairs: 155; year: 12, pairs: 150. The scatterplot shows a decreasing, non-linear trend of pairs versus year, starting at (1, 320) and ending at (12, 150). A reciprocal transformation applied to the variable pairs can also be used to linearise the scatterplot. When a least squares line is fitted to the plot of 1/pairs versus year, the largest difference between the actual value and the predicted value occurs at year A. 1 B. 2 C. 11 D. 12.",
        "answer": "A",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "A school runs an orientation program for new staff each January. The time series plot below shows the number of new staff, new, for each year, year, from 2011 to 2022 (inclusive). Data points: 2011: 14, 2012: 10, 2013: 8, 2014: 7, 2015: 9, 2016: 12, 2017: 13, 2018: 12, 2019: 9, 2020: 15, 2021: 12, 2022: 10. The time series is smoothed using seven-median smoothing. The smoothed value of new for the year 2016 is A. 10 B. 11 C. 12 D. 13",
        "answer": "A",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "A school runs an orientation program for new staff each January. The time series plot below shows the number of new staff, new, for each year, year, from 2011 to 2022 (inclusive). Data points: 2011: 14, 2012: 10, 2013: 8, 2014: 7, 2015: 9, 2016: 12, 2017: 13, 2018: 12, 2019: 9, 2020: 15, 2021: 12, 2022: 10. The number of new staff in 2023 is added to the total number of new staff from the previous 12 years. For these 13 years, the mean number of new staff is 11. The number of new staff in 2023 is A. 11 B. 16 C. 17 D. 19.",
        "answer": "B",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "The table below shows the total number of cans of soft drink sold each month at a suburban cafe in 2023. Table: Month 1: 316, 2: 321, 3: 365, 4: 306, 5: 254, 6: 308, 7: 354, 8: 357, 9: 381, 10: 355, 11: 365, 12: 324. The six-mean smoothed value of the number of cans sold, with centring, for month 5 is closest to A. 315 B. 318 C. 321 D. 324.",
        "answer": "C",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "The table below shows the seasonal indices for the monthly takings of a bistro. Table: Month 1: 1.08, 2: 1.13, 3: ?, 4: 0.92, 5: 0.67, 6: ?, 7: 1.09, 8: 1.35, 9: 0.82, 10: 0.88, 11: 1.01, 12: 0.98. The seasonal index for month 3 is twice the seasonal index for month 6. The seasonal index for month 3 is closest to A. 0.69 B. 1.04 C. 1.38 D. 2.07.",
        "answer": "C",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
        "topic": "Data analysis"
    },
    {
        "question": "A first-order linear recurrence relation of the form u₀ = a, uₙ₊₁ = R uₙ + d generates the terms of a sequence. A geometric sequence will be generated if A. R = 1 and d = -1 B. R = 1 and d = 1 C. R = 4 and d = -1 D. R = 2 and d = 0.",
        "answer": "D",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
        "topic": "Recursion and financial mathematics"
    },
    {
        "question": "Trevor took out a reducing balance loan of $400,000, with interest calculated weekly. The balance of the loan, in dollars, after n weeks, Tₙ, can be modelled by the recurrence relation T₀ = 400,000, Tₙ₊₁ = 1.00075 Tₙ – 677.55. Assume that there are exactly 52 weeks in a year. The interest rate, per annum, for this loan is A. 0.75% B. 3.9% C. 4.5% D. 7.5%.",
        "answer": "B",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
        "topic": "Recursion and financial mathematics"
    },
    {
        "question": "Liv bought a new car for $35,000. The value of the car will be depreciated by 18% per annum using the reducing balance method. A recurrence relation that models the year-to-year value of her car is of the form L₀ = 35,000, Lₙ₊₁ = k × Lₙ. The value of k is A. 0.0082 B. 0.18 C. 0.82 D. 1.18.",
        "answer": "C",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
        "topic": "Recursion and financial mathematics"
    },
    {
        "question": "Dainika invested $2000 for three years at 4.4% per annum, compounding quarterly. To earn the same amount of interest in three years in a simple interest account, the annual simple interest rate would need to be closest to A. 4.60% B. 4.68% C. 4.84% D. 4.98%.",
        "answer": "B",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
        "topic": "Recursion and financial mathematics"
    },
    {
        "question": "Lee took out a loan of $121,000, with interest compounding monthly. He makes monthly repayments of $2228.40 for five years until the loan is repaid in full. The total interest paid by Lee is closest to A. $4434 B. $5465 C. $10,539 D. $12,704.",
        "answer": "D",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
        "topic": "Recursion and financial mathematics"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stewart takes out a reducing balance loan of $240,000, with interest calculated monthly. Stewart makes regular monthly repayments. Three lines of the amortisation table are shown below: Payment number 0: Payment $0.00, Interest $0.00, Principal reduction $0.00, Balance $240,000.00; Payment number 1: Payment $2741.05, Interest $960.00, Principal reduction $1781.05, Balance $238,218.95; Payment number 2: Payment $2741.05, Interest not shown, Principal reduction not shown, Balance not shown. The principal reduction associated with Payment number 2 is closest to A. $1773.93 B. $1781.05 C. $1788.17 D. $2741.05.",
        "answer": "C",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
        "topic": "Recursion and financial mathematics"
    },
    {
        "question": "Stewart takes out a reducing balance loan of $240,000, with interest calculated monthly. Stewart makes regular monthly repayments. Three lines of the amortisation table are shown below: Payment number 0: Payment $0.00, Interest $0.00, Principal reduction $0.00, Balance $240,000.00; Payment number 1: Payment $2741.05, Interest $960.00, Principal reduction $1781.05, Balance $238,218.95; Payment number 2: Payment $2741.05, Interest not shown, Principal reduction not shown, Balance not shown. The number of years that it will take Stewart to repay the loan in full is closest to A. 9 B. 10 C. 11 D. 12.",
        "answer": "A",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
        "topic": "Recursion and financial mathematics"
    },
    {
        "question": "André invested $18,000 in an account for five years, with interest compounding monthly. He adds an extra payment into the account each month immediately after the interest is calculated. For the first two years, the balance of the account, in dollars, after n months, Aₙ, can be modelled by the recurrence relation A₀ = 18,000, Aₙ₊₁ = 1.002Aₙ + 100. After two years, André decides he would like the account to reach a balance of $30,000 at the end of the five years. He must increase the value of the monthly extra payment to achieve this. The minimum value of the new payment for the last three years is closest to A. $189.55 B. $195.45 C. $202.35 D. $246.55.",
        "answer": "A",
        "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
        "topic": "Recursion and financial mathematics"
    },
    {
        "question": "Matrix J is a 2 × 3 matrix. Matrix K is a 3 × 1 matrix. Matrix L is added to the product JK. The order of matrix L is A. 1 × 3 B. 2 × 1 C. 2 × 3 D. 3 × 2.",
        "answer": "B",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Matrices"
    },
    {
        "question": "A market stall sells three types of candles. The cost of each type of candle is shown in matrix C below: C = [25 32 43]. Towards the end of the day, the cost of each item is discounted by 15%. Which one of the following expressions can be used to determine each discounted price? A. 0.15C B. 0.85C C. 8.5C D. 15C.",
        "answer": "B",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Matrices"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following matrix, where h ≠ 0: [ [4, g], [8, h] ]. The inverse of this matrix does not exist when g is equal to A. -2h B. h/2 C. h D. 2h.",
        "answer": "B",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Matrices"
    },
    {
        "question": "Matrix J is a 2 × 3 matrix. Matrix K is a 3 × 1 matrix. Matrix L is added to the product JK. The order of matrix L is A. 1 × 3 B. 2 × 1 C. 2 × 3 D. 3 × 2.",
        "answer": "B",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Matrices"
    },
    {
        "question": "A primary school is hosting a sports day. Students represent one of four teams: blue (B), green (G), red (R), or yellow (Y). Students compete in one of three sports: football (F), netball (N), or tennis (T). Matrix W shows the number of students competing in each sport and the team they represent: W = [ [85, 60, 64, 71], [62, 74, 80, 64], [63, 76, 66, 75] ], where the columns are B, G, R, Y and the rows are F, N, T. Matrix W is multiplied by the column matrix [1, 1, 1, 1] to produce matrix X. Element x₃₁ indicates that A. 210 students represent the blue team. B. 210 students compete in netball. C. 280 students compete in tennis. D. 280 students compete in football.",
        "answer": "C",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Matrices"
    },
    {
        "question": "A tennis team consists of five players: Quinn, Rosie, Siobhan, Trinh and Ursula. When the team competes, players compete in the order of first, then second, then third, then fourth. The fifth player has a bye (does not compete). On week 1 of the competition, the players competed in the following order: First: Quinn, Second: Rosie, Third: Siobhan, Fourth: Trinh, Bye: Ursula. This information can be represented by matrix G₁ = [Q R S T U]. Let Gₙ be the order of play in week n. The playing order changes each week and can be determined by the rule Gₙ₊₁ = Gₙ × P, where P = [ [0 1 0 0 0], [0 0 0 0 1], [1 0 0 0 0], [0 0 1 0 0], [0 0 0 1 0] ]. Which player has a bye in week 4? A. Quinn B. Rosie C. Siobhan D. Trinh.",
        "answer": "C",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Matrices"
    },
    {
        "question": "Data has been collected on the female population of a species of mammal on a remote island. The female population has been divided into three age groups, with the initial population (at the time of data collection), the birth rate, and the survival rate of each age group shown in the table: Age group (years): 0–2, 2–4, 4–6; Initial population: 2100, 6400, 4260; Birth rate: 0, 1.8, 1.2; Survival rate: 0.7, 0.6, 0. The Leslie matrix (L) that may be used to model this particular population is A. L = [ [0, 1.8, 0], [0.7, 0, 1.2], [0, 0.6, 0] ] B. L = [ [0, 1.8, 1.2], [0.7, 0, 0], [0, 0.6, 0] ] C. L = [ [0, 1.8, 1.2], [0.7, 0.6, 0], [0, 0, 0] ] D. L = [ [2100, 6400, 4260], [0, 1.8, 1.2], [0.7, 0.6, 0] ].",
        "answer": "B",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Matrices"
    },
    {
        "question": "The matrix below shows the results of a round-robin chess tournament between five players: H, I, J, K, and L. In each game, there is a winner and a loser. Two games still need to be played. Matrix: rows and columns are H, I, J, K, L. H row: [0, 1, 0, 1, 0]; I row: [0, 0, …, 1, …]; J row: [1, …, 0, 1, 0]; K row: [0, 0, 0, 0, 1]; L row: [1, …, 1, 0, 0]. A ‘1’ in the matrix shows that the player named in that row defeated the player named in that column. A ‘…’ in the matrix shows that the player named in that row has not yet competed against the player in that column. At the end of the tournament, players will be ranked by calculating the sum of their one-step and two-step dominances. The player with the highest sum will be ranked first. The player with the second-highest sum will be ranked second, and so on. Which one of the following is not a potential outcome after the final two games have been played? A. Player I will be ranked first. B. Player I will be ranked fifth. C. Player J will be ranked first. D. Player J will be ranked fifth.",
        "answer": "D",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Matrices"
    },
    {
        "question": "A large sporting event is held over four consecutive days: Thursday, Friday, Saturday, and Sunday. People can watch the event at four different sites: Botanical Gardens (G), City Square (C), Riverbank (R), or Main Beach (M). Let Sₙ be the state matrix showing the number of people at each location n days after Thursday. The expected number of people at each location can be determined by the matrix recurrence rule Sₙ₊₁ = T Sₙ + A, where T = [ [0.4, 0.2, 0.4, 0], [0.4, 0.1, 0.3, 0.3], [0.1, 0.4, 0.1, 0.2], [0.1, 0.3, 0.2, 0.5] ] and A = [300, 200, 100, 300]. Given the state matrix S₃ = [5620 (G), 6386 (C), 4892 (R), 6902 (M)], the number of people watching the event at the Botanical Gardens (G) from Thursday to Sunday has A. decreased by 162 B. decreased by 212 C. increased by 124 D. increased by 696.",
        "answer": "D",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Matrices"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following graph (a simple undirected graph with 6 vertices, one of which is isolated, and one vertex has a loop). The sum of the degrees of the vertices is A. 10 B. 11 C. 12 D. 13.",
        "answer": "C",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Graphs and networks"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following graph (vertices A, B, C, D, E, F, with edges connecting A-B, A-C, B-C, B-D, C-D, C-F, D-E, D-F, E-F). A Eulerian trail through this graph could be A. ABCDEF B. ACBDCFDEF C. BACBDCFDEF D. BDCABCDFCDFEF.",
        "answer": "C",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Graphs and networks"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following graph (a simple undirected graph with 6 vertices, one of which is isolated, and one vertex has a loop). The sum of the degrees of the vertices is A. 10 B. 11 C. 12 D. 13.",
        "answer": "C",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Graphs and networks"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider the following graph (a planar connected graph with 7 vertices and 12 edges, forming several regions). The number of faces is A. 5 B. 6 C. 7 D. 8.",
        "answer": "B",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Graphs and networks"
    },
    {
        "question": "Eight houses in an estate are to be connected to the internet via underground cables. The network below shows the possible connections between the houses, with vertices A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H and edge weights representing cable lengths in metres: AB 15, AC 16, AD 20, BC 16, BG 19, CF 18, CG 14, CH 17, DE 19, DF 18, EF 20, EH 20, FG 18, FH 19, GH 18. The graph that represents the minimum length of cable needed to connect all the houses is A. a spanning tree connecting A-B, B-G, G-F, F-C, C-D, D-E, E-H B. a spanning tree connecting A-B, B-G, G-F, F-C, C-E, E-D, D-H C. a spanning tree connecting A-B, B-G, G-F, F-C, C-D, D-E, E-H D. a spanning tree connecting A-B, B-G, G-F, F-C, C-E, E-D, D-H.",
        "answer": "D",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Graphs and networks"
    },
    {
        "question": "The network below represents paths through a park from the carpark to a lookout. The vertices represent various attractions, and the numbers on the edges represent the distances between them in metres. The network is a weighted undirected graph with edges: carpark to first node (10), carpark to second node (7), carpark to third node (7), carpark to fourth node (x), first node to second node (11), first node to third node (5), first node to fourth node (8), second node to third node (8), second node to lookout (y), third node to fourth node (13), third node to lookout (7), fourth node to lookout (9), fourth node to third node (5), fourth node to lookout (8), third node to lookout (12), lookout to third node (7). The shortest path from the carpark to the lookout is 34 m. This can be achieved when A. x = 8 and y = 8 B. x = 9 and y = 7 C. x = 10 and y = 6 D. x = 11 and y = 5.",
        "answer": "D",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Graphs and networks"
    },
    {
        "question": "A connected graph has six vertices and six edges. How many of the following four statements must always be true? - the graph has no vertices of odd degree - the graph contains a Eulerian trail - the graph contains a Hamiltonian path - the sum of the degrees of the vertices is 12. A. 1 B. 2 C. 3 D. 4.",
        "answer": "A",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Graphs and networks"
    },
    {
        "question": "Anush, Blake, Carly and Dexter are workers on a construction site. They are each allocated one task. The time, in hours, it takes for each worker to complete each task is shown in the table: Task 1: Anush 12, Blake 10, Carly 11, Dexter 10; Task 2: Anush 8, Blake 7, Carly 10, Dexter 14; Task 3: Anush 16, Blake 15, Carly 18, Dexter 16; Task 4: Anush 9, Blake 10, Carly 12, Dexter 11. The tasks must be completed sequentially and in numerical order: Task 1, Task 2, Task 3, then Task 4. Management makes an initial allocation of tasks to minimise the amount of time required, but then decides that it takes the workers too long. Another worker, Edgar, is brought in to complete one of the tasks. His completion times, in hours, are: Task 1: 9, Task 2: 5, Task 3: 14, Task 4: 8. When a new allocation is made and Edgar takes over one of the tasks, the minimum total completion time compared to the initial allocation will be reduced by A. 1 hour B. 2 hours C. 3 hours D. 4 hours.",
        "answer": "D",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Graphs and networks"
    },
    {
        "question": "A project has 15 activities, A–O, that need to be completed. The directed network that represents this project is shown (a directed acyclic graph from start to finish with 15 nodes and multiple dependencies). Four possible activity tables are given. Table A: A–, B–, C–, D–, E:A, F:B, G:E,F,C,H, H:D, I:A, J:D, K:H, L:D, M:L, N:I,G,K,L, O:L. Table B: A:C, B:A, C–, D–, E:A, F:B,K,M,L, G:D, H–, I–, J:I, K:E,G,H,J, L:N, M:I, N:I, O:N. Table C: A:C, B:A, C–, D–, E:A, F:B,K,M,L, G:D, H–, I–, J:I, K:D,G,H,J, L:N, M:I, N:I, O:N. Table D: A:C, B:A, C–, D–, E:A, F:B,K,J,L, G:D, H–, I–, J:I, K:E,G,H,J, L:N, M:N, N:I, O:I.",
        "answer": "B",
        "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
        "topic": "Graphs and networks"
    },
      {
    "question": "Table 1 lists the Olympic year, year, and the gold medal-winning height for the men’s high jump, Mgold, in metres, for each Olympic Games held from 1928 to 2020. No Olympic Games were held in 1940 or 1944, and the 2020 Olympic Games were held in 2021.\n\nTable 1:\nyear | Mgold (m)\n1928 | 1.94\n1932 | 1.97\n1936 | 2.03\n1948 | 1.98\n1952 | 2.04\n1956 | 2.12\n1960 | 2.16\n1964 | 2.18\n1968 | 2.24\n1972 | 2.23\n1976 | 2.25\n1980 | 2.36\n1984 | 2.35\n1988 | 2.38\n1992 | 2.34\n1996 | 2.39\n2000 | 2.35\n2004 | 2.36\n2008 | 2.36\n2012 | 2.33\n2016 | 2.38\n2020 | 2.37\n\na. For the data in Table 1, determine:\ni. the maximum Mgold in metres\nii. the percentage of Mgold values greater than 2.25 m.",
    "answer": "2.39, 11/22*100% = 50%",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Table 1 lists the Olympic year, year, and the gold medal-winning height for the men’s high jump, Mgold, in metres, for each Olympic Games held from 1928 to 2020. No Olympic Games were held in 1940 or 1944, and the 2020 Olympic Games were held in 2021.\n\nTable 1:\nyear | Mgold (m)\n1928 | 1.94\n1932 | 1.97\n1936 | 2.03\n1948 | 1.98\n1952 | 2.04\n1956 | 2.12\n1960 | 2.16\n1964 | 2.18\n1968 | 2.24\n1972 | 2.23\n1976 | 2.25\n1980 | 2.36\n1984 | 2.35\n1988 | 2.38\n1992 | 2.34\n1996 | 2.39\n2000 | 2.35\n2004 | 2.36\n2008 | 2.36\n2012 | 2.33\n2016 | 2.38\n2020 | 2.37\n\nb. The mean of these Mgold values is 2.23 m, and the standard deviation is 0.15 m. Calculate the standardised z-score for the 2000 Mgold of 2.35 m.",
    "answer": "(2.35-2.23)/0.15",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Table 1 lists the Olympic year, year, and the gold medal-winning height for the men’s high jump, Mgold, in metres, for each Olympic Games held from 1928 to 2020. No Olympic Games were held in 1940 or 1944, and the 2020 Olympic Games were held in 2021.\n\nTable 1:\nyear | Mgold (m)\n1928 | 1.94\n1932 | 1.97\n1936 | 2.03\n1948 | 1.98\n1952 | 2.04\n1956 | 2.12\n1960 | 2.16\n1964 | 2.18\n1968 | 2.24\n1972 | 2.23\n1976 | 2.25\n1980 | 2.36\n1984 | 2.35\n1988 | 2.38\n1992 | 2.34\n1996 | 2.39\n2000 | 2.35\n2004 | 2.36\n2008 | 2.36\n2012 | 2.33\n2016 | 2.38\n2020 | 2.37\n\nc. Construct a boxplot for the Mgold data in Table 1 on the grid below. (Boxplot grid: x-axis labelled Mgold (m), scale from 1.92 to 2.40 in increments of 0.04)",
    "answer": "Boxplot with Min: 1.94, Q1: 2.12, Median: 2.29, Q3: 2.36, Max: 2.39",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Table 1 lists the Olympic year, year, and the gold medal-winning height for the men’s high jump, Mgold, in metres, for each Olympic Games held from 1928 to 2020. No Olympic Games were held in 1940 or 1944, and the 2020 Olympic Games were held in 2021.\n\nTable 1:\nyear | Mgold (m)\n1928 | 1.94\n1932 | 1.97\n1936 | 2.03\n1948 | 1.98\n1952 | 2.04\n1956 | 2.12\n1960 | 2.16\n1964 | 2.18\n1968 | 2.24\n1972 | 2.23\n1976 | 2.25\n1980 | 2.36\n1984 | 2.35\n1988 | 2.38\n1992 | 2.34\n1996 | 2.39\n2000 | 2.35\n2004 | 2.36\n2008 | 2.36\n2012 | 2.33\n2016 | 2.38\n2020 | 2.37\n\nd. A least squares line can also be used to model the association between Mgold and year. Using the data from Table 1, determine the equation of the least squares line for this data set. Use the template below to write your answer. Round the values of the intercept and slope to three significant figures. Template: Mgold = [intercept] + [slope] × year",
    "answer": "-7.97, 0.00516",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Table 1 lists the Olympic year, year, and the gold medal-winning height for the men’s high jump, Mgold, in metres, for each Olympic Games held from 1928 to 2020. No Olympic Games were held in 1940 or 1944, and the 2020 Olympic Games were held in 2021.\n\nTable 1:\nyear | Mgold (m)\n1928 | 1.94\n1932 | 1.97\n1936 | 2.03\n1948 | 1.98\n1952 | 2.04\n1956 | 2.12\n1960 | 2.16\n1964 | 2.18\n1968 | 2.24\n1972 | 2.23\n1976 | 2.25\n1980 | 2.36\n1984 | 2.35\n1988 | 2.38\n1992 | 2.34\n1996 | 2.39\n2000 | 2.35\n2004 | 2.36\n2008 | 2.36\n2012 | 2.33\n2016 | 2.38\n2020 | 2.37\n\ne. The coefficient of determination is 0.857. Interpret the coefficient of determination in terms of Mgold and year.",
    "answer": "85.7% of the variation in Mgold can be explained by the variation in year.",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
    {
    "question": "The boxplot below displays the distribution of all gold medal-winning heights for the women’s high jump, Wgold, in metres, for the 19 Olympic Games held from 1948 to 2020.\n\nBoxplot: x-axis labelled Wgold (m), scale from 1.64 to 2.08 in increments of 0.04. The box extends from about 1.88 to 2.02, with a median near 1.96. The lower whisker extends to about 1.72, and the upper whisker extends to about 2.04. There are no outliers shown.\n\na. Describe the shape of this data distribution.",
    "answer": "Negatively skewed",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The boxplot below displays the distribution of all gold medal-winning heights for the women’s high jump, Wgold, in metres, for the 19 Olympic Games held from 1948 to 2020.\n\nBoxplot: x-axis labelled Wgold (m), scale from 1.64 to 2.08 in increments of 0.04. The box extends from about 1.88 to 2.02, with a median near 1.96. The lower whisker extends to about 1.72, and the upper whisker extends to about 2.04. There are no outliers shown.\n\nb. For this boxplot, what is the smallest possible number of Wgold heights lower than 1.85 m?",
    "answer": "1",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The boxplot below displays the distribution of all gold medal-winning heights for the women’s high jump, Wgold, in metres, for the 19 Olympic Games held from 1948 to 2020.\n\nBoxplot: x-axis labelled Wgold (m), scale from 1.64 to 2.08 in increments of 0.04. The box extends from about 1.88 to 2.02, with a median near 1.96. The lower whisker extends to about 1.72, and the upper whisker extends to about 2.04. There are no outliers shown.\n\nc. i. Using the boxplot, show that the lower fence is 1.565 m and the upper fence is 2.325 m.\n\nc. ii. Referring to the boxplot, the lower fence and the upper fence, explain why no outliers exist.",
    "answer": "IQR = 2.04 – 1.85 = 0.19 Lower fence = 1.85 – 1.5 × 0.19 = 1.565 Upper fence = 2.04 + 1.5 × 0.19 = 2.325 and Both these values lie between the lower fence and upper fence so there are NO outliers.",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
    {
    "question": "The Olympic gold medal-winning height for the women’s high jump, Wgold, is often lower than the best height achieved in other international women’s high jump competitions in that same year. Table 2 lists the Olympic year, year, the gold medal-winning height, Wgold, in metres, and the best height achieved in all international women’s high jump competitions in that same year, Wbest, in metres, for each Olympic year from 1972 to 2020. A scatterplot of Wbest versus Wgold for this data is also provided.\n\nTable 2:\nyear | 1972 | 1976 | 1980 | 1984 | 1988 | 1992 | 1996 | 2000 | 2004 | 2008 | 2012 | 2016 | 2020\nWgold (m) | 1.92 | 1.93 | 1.97 | 2.02 | 2.03 | 2.02 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 1.97 | 2.04\nWbest (m) | 1.94 | 1.96 | 1.98 | 2.07 | 2.07 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 2.02 | 2.06 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.05\n\nScatterplot: Wbest (vertical axis, 1.92 to 2.10), Wgold (horizontal axis, 1.90 to 2.08), with points showing a positive linear association.\n\na. Name the response variable in this equation: When a least squares line is fitted to the scatterplot, the equation is found to be Wbest = 0.300 + 0.860 × Wgold. The correlation coefficient is 0.9318.",
    "answer": "Wbest",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Olympic gold medal-winning height for the women’s high jump, Wgold, is often lower than the best height achieved in other international women’s high jump competitions in that same year. Table 2 lists the Olympic year, year, the gold medal-winning height, Wgold, in metres, and the best height achieved in all international women’s high jump competitions in that same year, Wbest, in metres, for each Olympic year from 1972 to 2020. A scatterplot of Wbest versus Wgold for this data is also provided.\n\nTable 2:\nyear | 1972 | 1976 | 1980 | 1984 | 1988 | 1992 | 1996 | 2000 | 2004 | 2008 | 2012 | 2016 | 2020\nWgold (m) | 1.92 | 1.93 | 1.97 | 2.02 | 2.03 | 2.02 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 1.97 | 2.04\nWbest (m) | 1.94 | 1.96 | 1.98 | 2.07 | 2.07 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 2.02 | 2.06 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.05\n\nScatterplot: Wbest (vertical axis, 1.92 to 2.10), Wgold (horizontal axis, 1.90 to 2.08), with points showing a positive linear association.\n\nb. Draw the least squares line on the scatterplot.",
    "answer": "Line of best fit drawn on scatterplot; line must cover the range of Wgold values from 1.92 to 2.06 and extrapolate to correct edge intercepts",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Olympic gold medal-winning height for the women’s high jump, Wgold, is often lower than the best height achieved in other international women’s high jump competitions in that same year. Table 2 lists the Olympic year, year, the gold medal-winning height, Wgold, in metres, and the best height achieved in all international women’s high jump competitions in that same year, Wbest, in metres, for each Olympic year from 1972 to 2020. A scatterplot of Wbest versus Wgold for this data is also provided.\n\nTable 2:\nyear | 1972 | 1976 | 1980 | 1984 | 1988 | 1992 | 1996 | 2000 | 2004 | 2008 | 2012 | 2016 | 2020\nWgold (m) | 1.92 | 1.93 | 1.97 | 2.02 | 2.03 | 2.02 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 1.97 | 2.04\nWbest (m) | 1.94 | 1.96 | 1.98 | 2.07 | 2.07 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 2.02 | 2.06 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.05\n\nScatterplot: Wbest (vertical axis, 1.92 to 2.10), Wgold (horizontal axis, 1.90 to 2.08), with points showing a positive linear association.\n\nc. Determine the value of the coefficient of determination as a percentage. Round your answer to one decimal place.",
    "answer": "r² = (0.9318)² = 0.86825…",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Olympic gold medal-winning height for the women’s high jump, Wgold, is often lower than the best height achieved in other international women’s high jump competitions in that same year. Table 2 lists the Olympic year, year, the gold medal-winning height, Wgold, in metres, and the best height achieved in all international women’s high jump competitions in that same year, Wbest, in metres, for each Olympic year from 1972 to 2020. A scatterplot of Wbest versus Wgold for this data is also provided.\n\nTable 2:\nyear | 1972 | 1976 | 1980 | 1984 | 1988 | 1992 | 1996 | 2000 | 2004 | 2008 | 2012 | 2016 | 2020\nWgold (m) | 1.92 | 1.93 | 1.97 | 2.02 | 2.03 | 2.02 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 1.97 | 2.04\nWbest (m) | 1.94 | 1.96 | 1.98 | 2.07 | 2.07 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 2.02 | 2.06 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.05\n\nScatterplot: Wbest (vertical axis, 1.92 to 2.10), Wgold (horizontal axis, 1.90 to 2.08), with points showing a positive linear association.\n\nd. Describe the association between Wbest and Wgold in terms of strength and direction.\n\nstrength\n\ndirection",
    "answer": "Strong Positive",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Olympic gold medal-winning height for the women’s high jump, Wgold, is often lower than the best height achieved in other international women’s high jump competitions in that same year. Table 2 lists the Olympic year, year, the gold medal-winning height, Wgold, in metres, and the best height achieved in all international women’s high jump competitions in that same year, Wbest, in metres, for each Olympic year from 1972 to 2020. A scatterplot of Wbest versus Wgold for this data is also provided.\n\nTable 2:\nyear | 1972 | 1976 | 1980 | 1984 | 1988 | 1992 | 1996 | 2000 | 2004 | 2008 | 2012 | 2016 | 2020\nWgold (m) | 1.92 | 1.93 | 1.97 | 2.02 | 2.03 | 2.02 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 1.97 | 2.04\nWbest (m) | 1.94 | 1.96 | 1.98 | 2.07 | 2.07 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 2.02 | 2.06 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.05\n\nScatterplot: Wbest (vertical axis, 1.92 to 2.10), Wgold (horizontal axis, 1.90 to 2.08), with points showing a positive linear association.\n\ne. Referring to the equation of the least squares line, interpret the value of the slope in terms of the variables Wbest and Wgold.",
    "answer": "(On average), for each 1 m increase in Wgold, Wbest increases by 0.860 m",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Olympic gold medal-winning height for the women’s high jump, Wgold, is often lower than the best height achieved in other international women’s high jump competitions in that same year. Table 2 lists the Olympic year, year, the gold medal-winning height, Wgold, in metres, and the best height achieved in all international women’s high jump competitions in that same year, Wbest, in metres, for each Olympic year from 1972 to 2020. A scatterplot of Wbest versus Wgold for this data is also provided.\n\nTable 2:\nyear | 1972 | 1976 | 1980 | 1984 | 1988 | 1992 | 1996 | 2000 | 2004 | 2008 | 2012 | 2016 | 2020\nWgold (m) | 1.92 | 1.93 | 1.97 | 2.02 | 2.03 | 2.02 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 1.97 | 2.04\nWbest (m) | 1.94 | 1.96 | 1.98 | 2.07 | 2.07 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 2.02 | 2.06 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.05\n\nScatterplot: Wbest (vertical axis, 1.92 to 2.10), Wgold (horizontal axis, 1.90 to 2.08), with points showing a positive linear association.\n\nf. In 1984, the Wbest value was 2.07 m for a Wgold value of 2.02 m. Show that when this least squares line is fitted to the scatterplot, the residual value for this point is 0.0328.",
    "answer": "Predicted value = 0.300 + 0.860 × 2.02 = 2.0372 Residual = 2.07 – 2.0372 = 0.0328",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Olympic gold medal-winning height for the women’s high jump, Wgold, is often lower than the best height achieved in other international women’s high jump competitions in that same year. Table 2 lists the Olympic year, year, the gold medal-winning height, Wgold, in metres, and the best height achieved in all international women’s high jump competitions in that same year, Wbest, in metres, for each Olympic year from 1972 to 2020. A scatterplot of Wbest versus Wgold for this data is also provided.\n\nTable 2:\nyear | 1972 | 1976 | 1980 | 1984 | 1988 | 1992 | 1996 | 2000 | 2004 | 2008 | 2012 | 2016 | 2020\nWgold (m) | 1.92 | 1.93 | 1.97 | 2.02 | 2.03 | 2.02 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 1.97 | 2.04\nWbest (m) | 1.94 | 1.96 | 1.98 | 2.07 | 2.07 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 2.02 | 2.06 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.05\n\nScatterplot: Wbest (vertical axis, 1.92 to 2.10), Wgold (horizontal axis, 1.90 to 2.08), with points showing a positive linear association.\n\ng. The residual plot obtained when the least squares line was fitted to the data is shown below. The residual value from part f is missing from the residual plot.\n\nResidual plot: x-axis Wgold (m) from 1.90 to 2.08, y-axis residual from -0.02 to 0.04. Several points are plotted, showing a random scatter about zero.\n\ngi. Complete the residual plot by adding the residual value from part f, drawn as a cross (X), to the residual plot above.\ngii. In part b, a least squares line was fitted to the scatterplot. Does the residual plot from part g justify this? Briefly explain your answer.",
    "answer": "(Residual plot with cross at point (2.02, 0.0328)), Yes, the residual plot shows no clear pattern",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Olympic gold medal-winning height for the women’s high jump, Wgold, is often lower than the best height achieved in other international women’s high jump competitions in that same year. Table 2 lists the Olympic year, year, the gold medal-winning height, Wgold, in metres, and the best height achieved in all international women’s high jump competitions in that same year, Wbest, in metres, for each Olympic year from 1972 to 2020. A scatterplot of Wbest versus Wgold for this data is also provided.\n\nTable 2:\nyear | 1972 | 1976 | 1980 | 1984 | 1988 | 1992 | 1996 | 2000 | 2004 | 2008 | 2012 | 2016 | 2020\nWgold (m) | 1.92 | 1.93 | 1.97 | 2.02 | 2.03 | 2.02 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 1.97 | 2.04\nWbest (m) | 1.94 | 1.96 | 1.98 | 2.07 | 2.07 | 2.05 | 2.05 | 2.02 | 2.06 | 2.06 | 2.05 | 2.01 | 2.05\n\nScatterplot: Wbest (vertical axis, 1.92 to 2.10), Wgold (horizontal axis, 1.90 to 2.08), with points showing a positive linear association.\n\nh. In 1964, the gold medal-winning height, Wgold, was 1.90 m. When the least squares line is used to predict Wbest, it is found to be 1.934 m. Explain why this prediction is not likely to be reliable.",
    "answer": "extrapolation, 1.90 is outside the data range used to generate the least squares line",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
    {
    "question": "The time series plot below shows the gold medal-winning height for the women’s high jump, Wgold, in metres, for each Olympic year, year, from 1952 to 1988.\n\nTime series plot: x-axis labelled year, values from 1952 to 1988 in increments of 4 years; y-axis labelled Wgold (m), values from 1.60 to 2.05 in increments of 0.05. Data points are plotted for each Olympic year. The first two five-median smoothed points have been placed on the graph with crosses (X) and joined by a dashed line (---).\n\na. Complete the five-median smoothing by marking smoothed values with crosses (X) joined by a dashed line (---) on the time series plot above.",
    "answer": "(Five-median smoothing: last three points must be on top of data points, points must be joined by a dashed line)",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The time series plot below shows the gold medal-winning height for the women’s high jump, Wgold, in metres, for each Olympic year, year, from 1952 to 1988.\n\nTime series plot: x-axis labelled year, values from 1952 to 1988 in increments of 4 years; y-axis labelled Wgold (m), values from 1.60 to 2.05 in increments of 0.05. Data points are plotted for each Olympic year. The first two five-median smoothed points have been placed on the graph with crosses (X) and joined by a dashed line (---).\n\nb. Identify two qualitative features that best describe the time series plot above.",
    "answer": "increasing trend, irregular fluctuations",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS1",
    "topic": "Data analysis"
  },
    {
    "question": "Emi operates a mobile dog-grooming business. The value of her grooming equipment will depreciate. Based on average usage, a rule for the value, in dollars, of the equipment, Vn, after n weeks is Vn = 15000 – 60n. Assume that there are exactly 52 weeks in a year.\n\na. By what amount, in dollars, does the value of the grooming equipment depreciate each week?",
    "answer": "$60",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
    "topic": "Recursion and financial modelling"
  },
  {
    "question": "Emi operates a mobile dog-grooming business. The value of her grooming equipment will depreciate. Based on average usage, a rule for the value, in dollars, of the equipment, Vn, after n weeks is Vn = 15000 – 60n. Assume that there are exactly 52 weeks in a year.\n\nb. Emi plans to replace the grooming equipment after four years. What will be its value, in dollars, at this time?",
    "answer": "$15 000 – 4 × 52 × 60, 2520",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
    "topic": "Recursion and financial modelling"
  },
  {
    "question": "Emi operates a mobile dog-grooming business. The value of her grooming equipment will depreciate. Based on average usage, a rule for the value, in dollars, of the equipment, Vn, after n weeks is Vn = 15000 – 60n. Assume that there are exactly 52 weeks in a year.\n\nc. Vn is the value of the grooming equipment, in dollars, after n weeks. Write a recurrence relation in terms of V0, Vn+1 and Vn that can model this value from one week to the next.",
    "answer": "V₀ = 15 000, Vₙ₊₁ = Vₙ – 60",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
    "topic": "Recursion and financial modelling"
  },
  {
    "question": "Emi operates a mobile dog-grooming business. The value of her grooming equipment will depreciate. Based on average usage, a rule for the value, in dollars, of the equipment, Vn, after n weeks is Vn = 15000 – 60n. Assume that there are exactly 52 weeks in a year.\n\nd. The value of the grooming equipment decreases from one year to the next by the same percentage of the original $15,000 value. What is this annual flat rate percentage?",
    "answer": "(52*60)/15000 = 0.208 = 20.8%",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
    "topic": "Recursion and financial modelling"
  },
    {
    "question": "Emi invested profits of $10,000 into a savings account that earns interest compounding fortnightly, for one year. The effective interest rate, rounded to two decimal places, is 5.07%. Assume that there are exactly 26 fortnights in a year.\n\na. What is the nominal percentage rate of interest for the account? Round your answer to two decimal places.",
    "answer": "(5.07,26) = 4.9503…",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
    "topic": "Recursion and financial modelling"
  },
  {
    "question": "Emi invested profits of $10,000 into a savings account that earns interest compounding fortnightly, for one year. The effective interest rate, rounded to two decimal places, is 5.07%. Assume that there are exactly 26 fortnights in a year.\n\nb. Explain why the nominal interest rate appears lower than the effective interest rate.",
    "answer": "It does not take into account the fortnightly compounding",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
    "topic": "Recursion and financial modelling"
  },
    {
    "question": "Emi decides to invest a $300,000 inheritance into an annuity. Let En be the balance of Emi’s annuity after n months. A recurrence relation that can model the value of this balance from month to month is E0 = 300,000, En+1 = 1.003En – 2159.41.\n\na. Showing recursive calculations, determine the balance of the annuity after two months. Round your answer to the nearest cent.",
    "answer": "E0 = 300,000, E1 = 1.003(300,000) – 2159.41 = 300,000 – 2159.41 = 297,840.59, E2 = 1.003(297,840.59) – 2159.41 = 297,840.59 – 2159.41 = 295,681.18",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
    "topic": "Recursion and financial modelling"
  },
  {
    "question": "Emi decides to invest a $300,000 inheritance into an annuity. Let En be the balance of Emi’s annuity after n months. A recurrence relation that can model the value of this balance from month to month is E0 = 300,000, En+1 = 1.003En – 2159.41.\n\nb. For how many years will Emi receive the regular payment?",
    "answer": "From Finance Solver or Table of values, calculate 180 months, 15 years",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
    "topic": "Recursion and financial modelling"
  },
  {
    "question": "Emi decides to invest a $300,000 inheritance into an annuity. Let En be the balance of Emi’s annuity after n months. A recurrence relation that can model the value of this balance from month to month is E0 = 300,000, En+1 = 1.003En – 2159.41.\n\nc. Calculate the annual compound interest rate for this annuity.",
    "answer": "(1.003 – 1.000) × 12 × 100 = 3.6%",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
    "topic": "Recursion and financial modelling"
  },
  {
    "question": "Emi decides to invest a $300,000 inheritance into an annuity. Let En be the balance of Emi’s annuity after n months. A recurrence relation that can model the value of this balance from month to month is E0 = 300,000, En+1 = 1.003En – 2159.41.\n\nd. If Emi wanted the annuity to act as a perpetuity, what monthly payment, in dollars, would she receive?",
    "answer": "0.003 × 300 000 = $900",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
    "topic": "Recursion and financial modelling"
  },
    {
    "question": "Emi takes out a reducing balance loan of $500,000. The interest rate is 5.3% per annum, compounding monthly. Emi makes regular monthly repayments of $3071.63 for the duration of the loan, with only the final repayment amount being slightly different from all the other repayments. Determine the total cost of Emi’s loan, rounding your answer to the nearest cent. State the number of payments required to fully repay the loan.",
    "answer": "Working out: N = 288 I% = 5.3 PV = 500000 PMT = –3071.63 FV = 0 P/Y, C/Y = 12, 288 Total cost calculation: Total cost = 288 × $3071.63 + $4.18 Answers: Total cost = $884,633.62 Number of payments = 288",
    "learningArea": "U3AOS2",
    "topic": "Recursion and financial modelling"
  },
    {
    "question": "Vince works on a construction site. The amount Vince gets paid depends on the type of shift he works, as shown in the table below.\n\nShift type | Normal | Overtime | Weekend\nHourly rate of pay ($ per hour) | 36 | 54 | 72\n\nThis information is shown in matrix R below.\nR = [36 54 72]\n\na. Matrix RT is the transpose of matrix R. Write down matrix RT in the space below.",
    "answer": "[36,54,72]",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vince works on a construction site. The amount Vince gets paid depends on the type of shift he works, as shown in the table below.\n\nShift type | Normal | Overtime | Weekend\nHourly rate of pay ($ per hour) | 36 | 54 | 72\n\nThis information is shown in matrix R below.\nR = [36 54 72]\n\nDuring one week, Vince works 28 hours at the normal rate of pay, 6 hours at the overtime rate of pay, and 8 hours at the weekend rate of pay.\n\nb. Complete the following matrix calculation showing the total amount Vince has been paid for this week.\n[ ______  ______  ______ ] × RT = [ __________ ]",
    "answer": "Working: [28 6 8] × RT = [1908] Answer: 1908",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vince will receive $90 per hour if he works a public holiday shift. Matrix Q, as calculated below, can be used to show Vince’s hourly rate for each type of shift.\n\nQ = n × [1  1.5  2  p] = [36  54  72  90]\n\nc. Write the values of n and p in the boxes below.\nn =\np =",
    "answer": "n = 36 p = 2.5",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Matrices"
  },
    {
    "question": "To access the southern end of the construction site, Vince must enter a security code consisting of five numbers. The security code is represented by the row matrix W. The element in row i and column j of W is w_ij. The elements of W are determined by the rule (i – j)^2 + 2j.\n\na. Complete the following matrix showing the five numbers in the security code.\nW = [ ______  ______  ______  ______  ______ ]",
    "answer": "W = [2 5 10 17 26]",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "To access the northern end of the construction site, Vince enters a different security code, consisting of eight numbers. This security code is represented by the row matrix X. The element in row i and column j of X is x_ij. The elements of X are also determined by the rule (i – j)^2 + 2j.\n\nb. What is the last number in this security code to access the northern end of the construction site?",
    "answer": "Working: (1 – 8)² + 2 × 8 = 49 + 16 Answer: 65",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Matrices"
  },
    {
    "question": "A population of a native animal species lives near the construction site. To ensure that the species is protected, information about the initial female population was collected at the beginning of 2023. The birth rates and the survival rates of the females in this population were also recorded. This species has a life span of 4 years and the information collected has been categorised into four age groups: 0–1 year, 1–2 years, 2–3 years, and 3–4 years. This information is displayed in the initial population matrix, R0, and the Leslie matrix, L, below.\n\nR0 = [70, 80, 90, 40]^T\nL = [ [0.4, 0.75, 0.4, 0], [0.4, 0, 0, 0], [0, 0.7, 0, 0], [0, 0, 0.5, 0] ]\n\na. Using the information above\n i. complete the following transition diagram.\n (Diagram: four nodes labelled 0–1 year, 1–2 years, 2–3 years, 3–4 years, with arrows to be completed to show transitions between age groups and births.)\n\nii. complete the following table, showing the initial female population, and the predicted female population after one year, for each of the age groups.\n\n| Age group           | 0–1 year | 1–2 years | 2–3 years | 3–4 years |\n|---------------------|----------|-----------|-----------|-----------|\n| Initial population  |          |           |           |           |\n| Population after one year |    |           |           |           |",
    "answer": "Transition diagram with correct values: 0.4, 0.75, 0.4, 0.4, 0.7, 0.5, etc, Initial: 70 80 90 40 1 year: 124 28 56 45",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "It is predicted that if this species is not protected, the female population of each of the four age groups will rapidly decrease within the next 10 years. After how many years is it predicted that the total female population of this species will first be half the initial female population?",
    "answer": "Working: 131 < 0.5 × 280 Answer: 5",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Matrices"
  },
 {
    "question": "When the construction company established the construction site at the beginning of 2023, it employed 390 staff to work on the site. The staff comprised 330 construction workers (C), 50 foremen (F) and 10 managers (M). At the beginning of each year, staff can choose to stay in the same job, move to a different job on the site, or leave the site (L) and not return. The transition diagram below shows the proportion of staff who are expected to change their job at the site each year.\n\nTransition diagram: Four nodes labelled C, F, M, L. Arrows between nodes with the following proportions:\n- C to C: 0.3, C to F: 0.2, C to M: 0.2, C to L: 0.3\n- F to F: 0.2, F to C: 0.4, F to L: 0.4\n- M to M: 0.3, M to L: 0.7\n- L to L: 1.0\n\nThis situation can be modelled by the recurrence relation Sₙ₊₁ = T Sₙ, where\nT is the transitional matrix, S₀ = [330, 50, 10, 0]^T and n is the number of years after 2023.\n\nCalculate the predicted percentage decrease in the number of foremen (F) on the site from 2023 to 2025.",
    "answer": "No. foremen = 43 % decrease = (50 – 43) / 50 × 100 = 14%",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the construction company established the construction site at the beginning of 2023, it employed 390 staff to work on the site. The staff comprised 330 construction workers (C), 50 foremen (F) and 10 managers (M). At the beginning of each year, staff can choose to stay in the same job, move to a different job on the site, or leave the site (L) and not return. The transition diagram below shows the proportion of staff who are expected to change their job at the site each year.\n\nTransition diagram: Four nodes labelled C, F, M, L. Arrows between nodes with the following proportions:\n- C to C: 0.3, C to F: 0.2, C to M: 0.2, C to L: 0.3\n- F to F: 0.2, F to C: 0.4, F to L: 0.4\n- M to M: 0.3, M to L: 0.7\n- L to L: 1.0\n\n Determine the total number of staff on the site in the long term.",
    "answer": "Tⁿ × S₂₀₂₃ (for very large n) gives 390 as having left, Answer: 0",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "To encourage more construction workers (C) to stay, the construction company has given workers an incentive to move into the job of foreman (F). Matrix R below shows the ways in which staff are expected to change their jobs from year to year with this new incentive in place.\n\nMatrix R:\n        this year\n        C   F   M   L\nC   0.4 0.2 0   0\nF   0.4 0.2 0.4 0\nM   0   0.2 0.3 0\nL   0.2 0.4 0.3 1\n        next year\n\nThe site always requires at least 330 construction workers. To ensure that this happens, the company hires an additional 190 construction workers (C) at the beginning of 2024 and each year thereafter. The matrix Vₙ₊₁ will then be given by Vₙ₊₁ = R Vₙ + Z, where\nV₀ = [330, 50, 10, 0]^T\nZ = [190, 0, 0, 0]^T and n is the number of years after 2023.\n\nHow many more staff are there on the site in 2024 than there were in 2023?",
    "answer": "V₂₀₂₄ = 332 146 13 89 Extra staff = 190 – 89 = 101 Answer: 101",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Matrices"
  },
  {
    "question": "Based on this new model, the company has realised that in the long term there will be more than 200 foremen on site. In which year will the number of foremen first be above 200?",
    "answer": "No. foremen in 2027 = 200.54 Answer: 2027",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Matrices"
  },
    {
    "question": "A supermarket has five departments, with areas allocated as shown on the floorplan below.\n\nFloorplan: Deli (D), Bakery (B), General (G), Fresh produce (F), Promotional (P) are shown as separate areas. The floorplan is represented by the graph below. On this graph, vertices represent departments and edges represent boundaries between two departments. This graph is incomplete.\n\nGraph: Vertices D, B, G, F are shown, with edges connecting D-G, G-B, G-F, F-D.\n\nDraw the missing vertex and missing edges on the graph above. Include a label.",
    "answer": "MUST see two edges and vertex labelled as P on the graph",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Networks and decision mathematics"
  },
  {
    "question": "A supermarket has five departments, with areas allocated as shown on the floorplan below.\n\nFloorplan: Deli (D), Bakery (B), General (G), Fresh produce (F), Promotional (P) are shown as separate areas. The floorplan is represented by the graph below. On this graph, vertices represent departments and edges represent boundaries between two departments. This graph is incomplete.\n\nGraph: Vertices D, B, G, F are shown, with edges connecting D-G, G-B, G-F, F-D.\n\nKarla is standing in the Promotional department. She wants to visit each department in the supermarket once only.\n\nbi. In which department will she finish?\nbii. What is the mathematical name for this type of journey?",
    "answer": "P – F – D – G – B Answer: Bakery (Accept B), Hamilitonian path",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Networks and decision mathematics"
  },
  {
    "question": "A supermarket has five departments, with areas allocated as shown on the floorplan below.\n\nFloorplan: Deli (D), Bakery (B), General (G), Fresh produce (F), Promotional (P) are shown as separate areas. The floorplan is represented by the graph below. On this graph, vertices represent departments and edges represent boundaries between two departments. This graph is incomplete.\n\nGraph: Vertices D, B, G, F are shown, with edges connecting D-G, G-B, G-F, F-D.\n\nThe supermarket adds a new Entertainment department (E), and the floorplan is rearranged. The boundaries between the departments are represented in the adjacency matrix below, where a ‘1’ indicates a boundary between the departments.\n\nAdjacency matrix:\n    B D E F G P\nB [0 1 1 1 0 1]\nD [1 0 0 1 1 0]\nE [1 0 0 0 0 1]\nF [1 1 0 0 1 1]\nG [0 1 0 1 0 1]\nP [1 0 1 1 1 0]\n\nUse the adjacency matrix to complete the floorplan below by labelling each department. The Bakery (B) is already labelled.\n\nFloorplan: A rectangular arrangement with six regions, one labelled 'Bakery (B)', the others to be labelled.",
    "answer": "(Floorplan correctly labelled with D, E, F, G, P, Bakery (B))",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Networks and decision mathematics"
  },
    {
    "question": "A manufacturer (M) makes deliveries to the supermarket (S) via a number of storage warehouses, L, N, O, P, Q and R. These eight locations are represented as vertices in the network below. The numbers on the edges represent the maximum number of deliveries that can be made between these locations each day. Cut 1 is shown as a dashed line in the network.\n\nNetwork: Vertices M, L, N, O, P, Q, R, S. Edges with capacities: M-L (20), M-N (15), L-O (5), L-Q (13), N-P (12), O-Q (7), O-S (11), P-O (6), P-R (9), Q-S (14), R-S (8), Q-R (18).\n\na. When considering the possible flow of deliveries through this network, many different cuts can be made. Determine the capacity of Cut 1, shown above.",
    "answer": "Working: 13 + 18 + 6 + 9 Answer: 46",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Networks and decision mathematics"
  },
  {
    "question": "A manufacturer (M) makes deliveries to the supermarket (S) via a number of storage warehouses, L, N, O, P, Q and R. These eight locations are represented as vertices in the network below. The numbers on the edges represent the maximum number of deliveries that can be made between these locations each day. Cut 1 is shown as a dashed line in the network.\n\nNetwork: Vertices M, L, N, O, P, Q, R, S. Edges with capacities: M-L (20), M-N (15), L-O (5), L-Q (13), N-P (12), O-Q (7), O-S (11), P-O (6), P-R (9), Q-S (14), R-S (8), Q-R (18).\n\nb. Determine the maximum number of deliveries that can be made each day from the manufacturer to the supermarket.",
    "answer": "Working: Minimum cut = 13 + 5 + 11 + 8 Answer: 37",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Networks and decision mathematics"
  },
  {
    "question": "A manufacturer (M) makes deliveries to the supermarket (S) via a number of storage warehouses, L, N, O, P, Q and R. These eight locations are represented as vertices in the network below. The numbers on the edges represent the maximum number of deliveries that can be made between these locations each day. Cut 1 is shown as a dashed line in the network.\n\nNetwork: Vertices M, L, N, O, P, Q, R, S. Edges with capacities: M-L (20), M-N (15), L-O (5), L-Q (13), N-P (12), O-Q (7), O-S (11), P-O (6), P-R (9), Q-S (14), R-S (8), Q-R (18).\n\nc. The manufacturer wants to increase the number of deliveries to the supermarket. This can be achieved by increasing the number of deliveries between one pair of locations. Complete the following sentence by writing the locations in the boxes provided: To maximise this increase, the number of deliveries should be increased between locations [  ] and [  ].",
    "answer": "R, S (This pair in either order)",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Networks and decision mathematics"
  },
    {
    "question": "An upgrade to the supermarket requires the completion of 11 activities, A to K. The directed network below shows these activities and their completion time, in weeks. The minimum completion time for the project is 29 weeks.\n\nNetwork diagram: Nodes labelled start and finish, with directed edges labelled as follows: start to A (9), start to B (11), A to C (7), A to D (8), B to E (4), C to G (12), D to H (8), E to F (8), E to I (6), F to K (8), G to J (5), H to J (5), I to J (5), J to finish, K to finish.\n\na. Write down the critical path.",
    "answer": "A – C – H – J",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Networks and decision mathematics"
  },
  {
    "question": "An upgrade to the supermarket requires the completion of 11 activities, A to K. The directed network below shows these activities and their completion time, in weeks. The minimum completion time for the project is 29 weeks.\n\nNetwork diagram: Nodes labelled start and finish, with directed edges labelled as follows: start to A (9), start to B (11), A to C (7), A to D (8), B to E (4), C to G (12), D to H (8), E to F (8), E to I (6), F to K (8), G to J (5), H to J (5), I to J (5), J to finish, K to finish.\n\nb. Which activity can be delayed for the longest time without affecting the minimum completion time of the project?",
    "answer": "E can be delayed by 3 weeks Answer: E",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Networks and decision mathematics"
  },
  {
    "question": "A change is made to the order of activities. The table below shows the activities and their new latest starting times in weeks.\n\nActivity | Latest starting time (weeks)\nA | 0\nB | 2\nC | 10\nD | 9\nE | 13\nF | 14\nG | 18\nH | 17\nI | 19\nJ | 25\nK | 22\n\nA dummy activity is now required in the network.\n\nOn the directed network below, draw a directed edge to represent the dummy activity. Include a label.\n\nNetwork diagram: Nodes labelled start and finish, with directed edges labelled as follows: start to A (9), start to B (11), A to C (7), A to D (8), B to E (4), C to G (12), D to H (8), E to F (8), E to I (6), F to K (8), G to J (5), H to J (5), I to J (5), J to finish, K to finish.",
    "answer": "MUST have correct arrow Line can be solid or dashed Label as \"dummy\" or \"d\" or “D’ “ or “d’ “.",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Networks and decision mathematics"
  },
  {
    "question": "A change is made to the order of activities. The table below shows the activities and their new latest starting times in weeks.\n\nActivity | Latest starting time (weeks)\nA | 0\nB | 2\nC | 10\nD | 9\nE | 13\nF | 14\nG | 18\nH | 17\nI | 19\nJ | 25\nK | 22\n\nA dummy activity is now required in the network.\n\nWhat is the new minimum completion time of the project?",
    "answer": "New critical path is A – D – H – J Answer: 30 weeks",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Networks and decision mathematics"
  },
  {
    "question": "A change is made to the order of activities. The table below shows the activities and their new latest starting times in weeks.\n\nActivity | Latest starting time (weeks)\nA | 0\nB | 2\nC | 10\nD | 9\nE | 13\nF | 14\nG | 18\nH | 17\nI | 19\nJ | 25\nK | 22\n\nThe owners of the supermarket want the project completed earlier. They will pay to reduce the time of some of the activities. A reduction in completion time of an activity will incur an additional cost of $10,000 per week. Activities can be reduced by a maximum of two weeks. The minimum number of weeks an activity can be reduced to is seven weeks. What is the minimum amount the owners of the supermarket will have to pay to reduce the completion time of the project as much as possible?",
    "answer": "Activities reduced (weeks): A (–2), D (–1), H (–1), B (–1) Total cost = 5 × $10,000 = $50,000 Answer: $50,000",
    "learningArea": "U4AOS1",
    "topic": "Networks and decision mathematics"
  }
    ]
}